Serge Grigoriev/Ballets Russes Archive
Music Division, Library of Congress
- Photographs (Boxes 9; 14; 17-18; 20; 23-24)
  - Personal Names (Box 9; 14; 17-18; 20; 23-24)
    - Lifar, Serge; Tchernicheva, Lubov; Nikitina, Alice; and Doubrovska, Felia (Box 9)
    - Lifar, Serge; Ansermet, Ernest; Nikitina, Alice; Doubrovska, Felia; and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 9)
    - Lloyd, Barbara (Box-folder 24/6)
    - Mackenzie, Kenneth (Box-folder 24/5)
    - Mackenzie, Kenneth and other (Box-folder 24/6)
    - Mackenzie, Kenneth and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 18)
    - Mackenzie, Kenneth; Jasinski, Roman; and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 18)
    - Marra, Eleanora (Box 9)
    - Massine, Léonide (Box 20)
    - Massine, Léonide and Grigorieva, Tamara (Box 14)
    - Massine, Léonide and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 14)
    - Massine, Léonide; Nemchinova, Vera; and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 20)
    - Mordkin, Mikhail (Box-folder 23/17)
    - Morosova, Olga (Box-folder 24/3; 7)
    - Morosova, Olga and Grigorieva, Tamara (Box 14)
    - Morosova, Olga; Zorina, Vera; and Strogova, Pauline (Box 14)
    - Morosova, Olga and others (Box 18)
    - Nelidova, Vera [Cuff, Betty] (Box 17)
    - Nelidova, Vera; Grigorieva, Tamara; Tchinarova, Tamara (Box 14)
    - Nemchinova, Vera (Box-folder 23/18; 17)
    - Nemchinova, Vera and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box-folder 23/30)
    - Nemchinova, Vera; Massine, Léonide; and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 20)
    - Nijinska, Bronislava (Box-folder 23/19)
    - Nijinsky, Vaslav (Box-folder 23/20)
    - Nijinsky, Vaslav (with his family) (Box-folder 23/21)
    - Nikitina, Alice (Box-folder 23/22)
    - Nikitina, Alice; Tchernicheva, Lubov; Doubrovska, Felia; and Lifar, Serge (Box 9)
    - Osato, Sono (Box-folder 24/3; 17)
    - Panaiev, Michel (Box-folder 24/6)
    - Petroff, Paul (Box-folder 23/23; 23/2; 17; 18)
    - Petroff, Paul and Baronova, Irina (Box-folder 23/2)
    - Petroff, Paul and Danilova, Alexandra (Box 14)
    - Petroff, Paul and Grigorieva, Tamara (Box 14)
    - Petroff, Paul and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 17; 18)
    - Petroff, Paul; Tchernicheva, Lubov; and Rostov, Dmitri (Box 18)
    - Riabouchinska, Tatiana (Box-folder 24/3; 24/4; 17)
    - Riabouchinska, Tatiana and Gilpin, John (?) (Box-folder 23/24)
    - Riabouchinska, Tatiana and Lichine, David (Box-folder 24/6)
    - Riabouchinska, Tatiana and Toumanova, Tamara (Box 17)
    - Riabouchinska, Tatiana; Toumanova, Tamara; and Verchinina, Nina (Box 17)
    - Riabouchinska, Tatiana; Toumanova, Tamara; Lichine, David; and Grigorieva, Tamara (Box 14)
    - Rostov, Dmitri (Box-folder 24/5; 17)
    - Rostov, Dmitri and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 17)
    - Rostov, Dmitri; Tchernicheva, Lubov; and Petroff, Paul (Box 18)
    - Rostov, Dmitri; Tchernicheva, Lubov; and Borovansky, Edouard (Box 18)
    - Rostova, Lubov and others (Box 18)
    - Sand, Inge (Box-folder 24/1)
    - Schwezoff, Igor (Box-folder 24/6)
    - Siniavine, Alec (Box-folder 23/25)
    - Skibine, George (Box-folder 23/26)
    - Skibine, George and others (Box 17)
    - Slavenska, Mia; Grigoriev, Serge and Vladimir; and Tchernicheva; Lubov (Box 9)
    - Stepanova,Tatiana (Box-folder 24/1)
    - Stogonova, Nina and Grigorieva, Tamara (Box 14)
    - Tcherkas, Constantin; Doubrovska, Felia; and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 9)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box-folder 23/27; 9; 16; 18)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov (head shots) (Box-folder 23/28)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov (with others) (Box-folder 23/29; 16; 17; 18; 20)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov; Ansermet, Ernest; Doubrovska, Felia; Lifar, Serge; and Nikitina, Alice (Box 9)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov; Balanchine, George; and Doubrovska, Felia (Box 9)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov; Danilova, Alexandra; Grigoriev; and Doubrovska, Felia (Box 9)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov and Nemchinova, Vera (Box-folder 23/30)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov; Nemchinova, Vera; and Massine, Léonide (Box 20)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov and Grigoriev, Serge (Box-folder 23/31; 18; 9)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov and Massine, Léonide (Box 14)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov and Petroff, Paul (Box 17; 18)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov and Jasinski, Roman (Box 18)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov; Jasinski, Roman; and Mackenzie, Kenneth (Box 18)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov; Nikitina, Alice; Doubrovska, Felia; and Lifar, Serge (Box 9)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov and Mackenzie, Kennneth (Box 18)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov and Rostov, Dmitri (Box 17)
    - Tchernicheva, Lubov (in various works) (Box-folder 23/32)
    - Tchinarova, Tamara; Grigorieva; and Nelidova, Vera (Box 14)
    - Tchinarova, Tamara and others (Box 18)
    - Toumanova, Tamara (Box-folder 23/33; 17)
    - Toumanova, Tamara and Riabouchinska, Tatiana (Box 17)
    - Toumanova, Tamara; Riabouchinska, Tatiana; Lichine, David; and Grigorieva, Tamara (Box 14)
    - Toumanova, Tamara; Verchina, Nina; and Riabouchinska, Tatiana (Box 7)
    - Tupine, Oleg (Box-folder 23/34; 24/1; 24/5)
    - Verchinina, Nina (Nina Verchinina de Beausacq) (Box 17)
    - Verchinina,Nina and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 9)
    - Verchinina, Nina; Toumanova, Tamara; and Riabouchinska, Tatiana (Box 17)
    - Volkova, Anna and others (Box 18)
    - Woizikowski, Leon [Leon Wójcikowski] (Box 9)
    - Zorina, Vera; Morosova, Olga; and Hyman, Prudence (Box 14)
    - Zorina, Vera and others (Box 18)
    - Zvereff, Nicholas (Box-folder 23/35)
    - Unidentifed (non-dance) (Box-folder 23/36)
    - Unidentified groups (Box-folder 23/37)
  - Choreographic Works (Boxes 9; 14; 17-18; 20; 23-24)
    - L’ Après-midi d’un Faune (Box 14)
    - Aurora’s Wedding (Box-folder 24/1; 14)
    - Blue Danube (Box 14)
    - Les Biches (Box-folder 23/17)
    - Cain and Abel (Box 18)
    - Carousal (Box-folder 23/14)
    - Cendrillon (Box 18)
    - Les Cent Baisers (Box-folder 23/1; 23/2; 14)
    - Le Chant du Rossigno (Box-folder 23/12; 20)
    - Choreartium (Box-folder 24/2; 14)
    - Le Coq d’Or (Box-folder 24/3)
    - Danses Slaves et Tziganes (Box 14)
    - La Fille du Pharaon (Box-folder 23/14)
    - The Firebird (Box-folder 24/4; 14)
    - Francesca da Rimini (Box-folder 24/5; 23/32; 16; 17; 18)
    - The Good-Humored Ladies (Box 5)
    - Graduation Ball (Box-folder 24/6; 7)
    - Icare (Box-folder 24/7)
    - Les Noces (Box-folder 24/8; 20)
    - Paganini (Box-folder 24/9; 17; 18)
    - Les Papillons (Box-folder 23/1)
    - Pavana (Box 17)
    - Petruchka (Box-folder 23/21; 23/27; 17)
    - Les Présages (Box-folder 24/10; 14)
    - Pulcinella (Box 20)
    - Romeo and Juliet (Box-folder 23/32)
    - Shéhérazade (Box-folder 23/20; 9; 14; 17; 18)
    - Le Soleil de Nuit [later Midnight Sun] (Box 14)
    - Le Spectre de la Rose (Box-folder 23/24)
    - Les Sylphides (Box-folder 24/11; 23/32)
    - Swan Lake (Box-folder 24/12)
    - Symphonie Fantastique (Box-folder 24/13; 23/1)
    - Thamar (Box 17; 18)
    - Le Tricorne (Box 18)
    - Unidentified Works (Box-folder 24/14)
- Photograph Albums (Boxes 7-9; 13-22)
  This series contains albums that span the dates 1916 to 1948 and include nearly 3,000 of Serge Grigoriev’s photographs of ballet dancers and colleagues in the Ballets Russes de Serge Diaghilev and the Ballets Russes de Monte Carlo. Some are signed and many are unpublished. Included are photographs of George Balanchine, Irina Baronova, Alexandra Danilova, Colonel W. De Basil, Serge Diaghilev, Vladimir Dokoudovsky, Serge Gregoriev, Tamara Grigorieva, David Lichine, Serge Lifar, Léonide Massine, Vera Nemchinova, Bronislava Nijinska, Vaslav Nijinsky, Tatiana Riabouchinska, Tamara Toumanova, and Vera Zorina, just to name a few.
  The albums also contain photographs of the company in locations around the world, including Monte-Carlo, Montreux, Roquebrune, Berlin, Edinburgh, London, Barcelona, Montserrat, Paris, Guadalajara, Santiago (Chile), Rio de Janeiro, Havana, New York, Lima, La Paz, Buenos Aires, Quito, Bogota, Caracas, Bombay, Melbourne, and Sydney as well as cities throughout Samoa, Ceylon, Central America, Aden, the United States, and New Zealand. Of particular interest is the scrapbook of passport or identification photographs that identify the dancers by their original names.
  The albums are rich in performance photographs of works that include Francesca da Reminit, Schéhérazade, Thamar, The Firebird, Paganini, Cendrillon, Cain and Abel, Les Cent Baisers, Aurora’s Wedding, L’Après-midi d’un Faune, Les Présages, Choréartium, Petrouchka, Good Humoured Ladies, Danses Slaves, Blue Danube, Swan Lake, Pulcinella, Le Chant du Rossignol, Les Noces, Petrouchka, and include photographs of the costume and/or set designs for Zéphire et Flore, Renard, Les Biches, Les Fâcheux, and Barabau.
  - Family photographs, locations (1916) (Box 7)
  - Uncaptioned, undated photographs of locations, Grigoriev family (1917) (Box 8)
  - Monte-Carlo, Montreux, Berlin, Edinburgh, Paris, London, Barcelona, Montserrat, 1935 and 1936 tours of U.S. (1918-1935) (Box 9)
  - Uncaptioned, undated photographs of locations and of the Ballets Russes in performance (1919-1920-1921) (Box 13)
  - 1935 and 1936-1937 tours of US; Barcelona performance photographs of Schérérazade, Les Cent Baisers, Aurora’s Wedding, L’Apres-midi d’un Faune, Les Présages, Chorertium, Good Humored Ladies, Firebird, Danses Slaves et Tziganes, Blue Danube, and Swan Lake. (1935-1938) (Box 14)
  - London, Paris, Italy, 1938 American tour; Ceylon, Australia, India, New Zealand, Aden (1936-1940) (Box 15)
  - Australia, London, Schérérazade and Francesca da Rimini; portraits of numerous dancers, including Toumanova, Riabouchinska, Verchinina, Nemchinova, Denisova, Lifar, Lichine, de Basil, Gregoriev, as well as performance shots of Paganini, Pavana, Graduation Ball, and Petruchcka (1939-1940) (Box 17)
  - Lubov Tchernicheva (and others) in Francesca da Rimini (1940 Australia tour) (1939-1940) (Box 16)
  - Performance shots of Lubov Tchernicheva in Francesca da Rimini, Thamar, Schérérazade, Paganini, Cendrillon, Cain and Abel. Photographs of other dancers include Paul Petroff, Roman Jasinski, Kenneth MacKenzie, Dmitri Rostov, David Lichine, and Edouard Borovansky. This album contains full company and performance shots in Buenos Aires (1944) (1944-1946) (Box 18)
  - Samoa, Havana, Mexico, Chile, Brazil, Columbia, Argentina, Peru, Bolivia, Uruguay, Equador, Venezuela, Panama, Costa Rica, Honduras, Guatemala, Spain (1940-1948) (Box 19)
  - Album of undated, uncaptioned photographs (n.d.) (Box 20)
  - Performance photographs and/or illustrations of set designs for Pulcinella, Le Chant du Rossignol, Les Noces, Zéphire et Flore, Mavra, Renard, Les Biches, Les Facheux, and Barabau (n.d.) (Box 21)
  - Headshots of members of Ballets Russes (possibly passport or identification photos; 2 albums) (n.d.) (Box 22)
- Programs (Box 11)
  This series contains programs and souvenir programs for Colonel W. de Basil’s Ballets Russes (also known as the Original Ballet Russe) and for Sergei J. Denham’s company, the Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo (1938-1962). For original souvenir programs for Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes’s premiere performance of The Firebird (1910) and a 1924 performance at La Scala, see Box 226 in the Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge Collection.
  - Théatre de la Danse – La Nijinska, Ballets Russes 1934; Souvenir Program (Box-folder 11/1)
  - Col. W. de Basil’s Ballets Russes, 1936-1937; Souvenir Program (Box-folder 11/2)
  - Col. W. de Basil’s Ballets Russes, 1937 (Box-folder 11/3)
  - Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, 1941 (Box-folder 11/4)
  - Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, 1941; Program Supplement (Box-folder 11/5)
  - Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, 1943-1944; Souvenir Program (Box-folder 11/6)
  - Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, 1944; Souvenir Program for Song of Norway (Box-folder 11/7)
  - Original Ballet Russe, 1946 (Box-folder 11/8)
  - Original Ballet Russe, 1946; Souvenir Program (Box-folder 11/9)
  - Original Ballet Russe, 1946-1947; Souvenir Program (Box-folder 11/10)
  - Loose pages and covers from various souvenir programs (Box-folder 11/11)
- Writings about the Ballets Russes de Serge Diaghilev and the Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo (Box 12)
  This series contains publications about two of the famous Russian dance companies: the Ballets Russes de Serge Diaghilev (known also as Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes) and the Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, a company that was created for Léonide Massine upon his departure from Ballets Russes de Colonel W. De Basil. This company was led by Sergei J. Denham and existed from 1938 to 1962.
  - Advertising flyer, The Diaghilev Ballet, 1909-1929, by S.L. Grigoriev (Box-folder 12/1)
  - Maynard, Olga. Petrouchka: Diaghilev’s 1911, Joffrey’s 1970, n.d. (Box-folder 12/2)
  - Blanche, Jacques-Emile. Leon Bakst dans le Ballet Russe, n.d. (incomplete) (Box-folder 12/3)
  - Anderson, Jack, Janet Light, and Malcolm McCormick. The Golden Age of Costume and Set Design for the Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, 1938-1944. Cincinnati Art Museum, 2002 (Box-folder 12/4)
  - Art et Danse, no. 4, Juin-Juillet 1959 (Box-folder 12/5)
  - Schaikevitch, Andre. "Le Destin du Ballet de L’Opera," in La Revue Musicale, pp. 278-279, 1971 (Box-folder 12/6)
  - Lifar, Serge. Undated, holograph document (two pages in ink); fragmentary discussion on Prokofiev and Le Fils Prodigue (1929) and an assessment of choreographer Léonide Massine. [Photocopy of original, which can be found in ML95.L54 no. 1] (Box-folder 12/7)
  - Schouvaloff, Alexander. Serge Diaghilev: The Centenary Exhibition of Les Ballets Russes. The Daniel Katz Gallery, London, 2009 (Box-folder 12/8)
  - Jeschke, Claudia, ed. Schwane und Feuervögel: Die Ballets Russes 1909-1929, Munich, 2009 (Box-folder 12/9)
  - Exhibition brochures: Library of Congress (2009); New York Public Library for the Performing Arts (2009) (Box-folder 12/10)
  - Bloom, Julie. “Admiring the Man Who Made Ballet Modern,” in The New York Times, 23 August, 2009 (Box-folder 12/11)
- Ballets Russes: Company members; Clippings; Tour Information; Drawings (Box 10)
  This series contains miscellaneous materials relating to Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes (1909-1929) and the Ballets Russes de Monte Carlo (also known as various other names including the Original Ballet Russe, 1932-1952).
  - Receipt acknowledging payment from Serge Diaghilev to Vaslav Nijinsky, 1917 (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Clippings (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Tour Information (Box-folder 10/3)
  - Notebook of drawings of members of the Ballets Russes by Grant MacDonald (Box-folder 10/4)
  - Salary list, undated (Box-folder 10/5)
  - Personal papers (Grigoriev) (Box-folder 10/6)
  - Drawings and other images (Box-folder 10/7)
  - Choreographic notes for Graduation Ball, choreographed by David Lichine in 1940, Choreographed for the original Ballets Russes. (Box-folder 10/8)
Appendix A: Names Associated with the Serge Grigoriev/Ballets Russes Archive
(Where appropriate, full and correct forms of original names, if known, appear in parentheses)
Algeranoff, Harcourt (Harcourt Essex)
Alonso, Alberto
Ansermet, Ernest
Balanchine, George (Georgii Meltonovich Balanchivadze)
Baronova, Irina (Irina Mikhailovna Baronova)
Borovansky, Edouard
Bousloff, Serge
Conus, Natalie
Danilova, Alexandra (Aleksandra Dionisievna Danilova)
De Basil, Colonel Wassily
Denisova, Alexandra (Patricia Denise Meyers; also known as Patricia Meyers and as Patricia Denise)
Diaghilev, Serge (Sergei Pavlovich Diagilev)
Dokoudovsky, Vladimir
Doroudovsky, M.
Doubrovska, Felia (Felitsata Leont’evna Diuzhnevskaia)
Federov, Michel
Geltser, Ekaterina (Ekaterina Vasil’evna Gel’tser)
Gilpin, John
Grigoriev, Serge (Sergei Leonidovich Grigor’ev)
Grigorieva, Tamara
Hyman, Prudence (also known as Pauline Strogova)
Jasinski, Roman (Roman Czesław Jasińslo)
Karlewska, Jadwiga
Karsavina, Tamara
Kochno, Boris
Kshessinska, Matilda (Matil’da-Mariia Feliksovna Kshesinskaia)
Kyasht, Lydia (Lidiia Georgievna Kiakst)
Lazowski, Yurek
Leskova, Tatiana
Lichine, David (David Kikhtenshtein)
Lifar, Serge (Sergei Mikhailovich Serdkin)
Lloyd, Barbara
Mackenzie, Kenneth
Marra, Eleanora
Mordkin, Mikhail (Mikhail Mikhailovich Mordkin)
Morosova, Olga
Nelidova, Vera [Cuff, Betty]
Nemchinova, Vera
Nijinska, Bronislava (Bronislava Fominichna Nizhinskaia)
Nijinsky, Vaslav (Vatslav Fomich Nizhinskii)
Nikitina, Alice
Osato, Sono
Panaiev, Michel
Petroff, Paul
Riabouchinska, Tatiana (Tat’iana Riabushinskaia)
Rostov, Dmitri
Rostova, Lubov (Lucienne Kylberg)
Sand, Inge (Inge Sand Sørensen)
Schwezoff, Igor (Igor’ Shvetsov)
Siniavine, Alec
Skibine, George (Iurii Borisovich Skibin)
Slavenska, Mia (Mia Čorak)
Stepanova, Tatiana
Stogonova, Nina (Nina Rigmor Strom)
Tcherkas, Constantin
Tchernicheva, Lubov (Liubov’ Pavlovna Chernyshova)
Tchinarova, Tamara
Toumanova, Tamara (Tamara Vladimirovna Tumanova)
Tupine, Oleg
Verchinina, Nina (Nina Verchinina de Beausacq)
Volkova, Anna
Woizikowski, Leon (Leon Wójcikowski)
Zorina, Vera (Eva Brigitta Hartwig)
Zvereff, Nicholas
Appendix B: Choreographic Works Associated with the Serge Grigoriev/Ballets Russes Archive
L’Amour Sorcier
Choreographer: Leon Woizikowsky; Music: Manuel de Falla: Premiere: 21 November 1936, Her Majesty’s Theatre, Melbourne, Australia
L’Après-midi d’un Faune
Choreographer: Vaslav Nijinsky; Music: Claude Debussy; Premiere: 29 May 1912, Théâtre du Châtelet, Paris
Aurora’s Wedding
One-act version of The Sleeping Beauty; Premiere: 1922
Le Bal
Choreographer: George Balanchine; Music: Vittorio Rieti; Premiere: 7 May 1929, Théâtre de Monte-Carlo, Monte Carlo
Balustrade
Choreographer: George Balanchine; Music: Igor Stravinsky; Premiere: 22 January 1941, Fifty-first Street Theatre, New York
Barabau
Choreographer: George Balanchine; Music: Vittorio Rieti; Premiere: 11 December 1925, Coliseum Theatre, London
Beach
Choreographer: Léonide Massine; Music: Françaix; Premiere: 1933
Le Beau Danube [Blue Danube]
Choreographer: Léonide Massine; Music: Johann Strauss; Premiere: 1924; expanded and staged under title Le Beau Danube Bleu, 1933
Les Biches
Choreographer: Bronislava Nijinska; Music: Francis Poulenc; Premiere: 6 January 1924, Théâtre de Monte-Carlo, Monte Carlo
Cain and Abel
Choreographer: David Lichine; Music: Richard Wagner; Premiere: 1946
Carnaval
Choreographer: Michel Fokine; Music: Robert Schumann, orchestrated by Anton Arensky, Alexander Glazunov, Anatol Liadov, Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov, Nicholas Tcherepnine; Premiere: 20 February 1910, Pavlov Hall, Saint Petersburg; Ballets Russes premiere: 20 May 1910, Theater des Westens, Berlin
Carousal
Cendrillon
Choreographer: Michel Fokine; Music: Frédéric d’Erlanger; Premiere: 1938
Les Cent Baisers
Choreographer: Bronislava Nijinska; Music: Frédéric d’Erlanger; Premiere: 18 July 1935, Covent Garden, London
Le Chant du Rossignol
Choreographer: Léonide Massine; Music: Igor Stravinsky; Premiere: 2 February 1920, Théâtre National de l’Opéra, Paris
Choreartium
Choreographer: Léonide Massine; Music: Johannes Brahms; Premiere: 1933
Cléopâtra
Choreographer: Michel Fokine; Music: Anton Arensky, with additional music by others; Premiere: 2 June 1909, Théâtre du Châtelet, Paris
La Concurrence
Choreographer: George Balanchine; Music: Georges Auric; Premiere: 12 April 1932, Théâtre de Monte-Carlo, Monte Carlo
Le Coq d’Or (opera)
Choreographer: Michel Fokine; Music: Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov; Premiere: 24 May 1914, Théâtre National de l’Opéra, Paris
Contes Russes
Choreographer: Léonide Massine; Music: Anatoly Liadov; Premiere: 11 May 1917, Théâtre du Châtelet, Paris
Cotillon
Choreographer: George Balanchine; Music: Emmanuel Chabrier; Premiere: 12 April 1932
Danses Slaves et Tziganes
Choreographer: Bronislava Nijinska; Music: divertissement from opera Russalka with music by Alexander Sergeyevich Dargomïzhsky; Premiere: 1936
Danzas Eslavas
École de Dance
Les Fâcheux
Choreographer: Bronislava Nijinska; Music: Georges Auric; Premiere: 19 January 1924, Théâtre de Monte-Carlo, Monte Carlo
La Fille du Pharaon
Choreographer: Marius Petipa; Music: Cesare Pugni; Premiere: Bolshoi Theatre, Saint Petersburg, 1862
The Firebird
Choreographer: Michel Fokine; Music: Igor Stravinsky; Premiere: 25 June 1910, Théâtre National de l’Opéra, Paris
Francesca da Rimini
Choreographer: Michel Fokine; Music: Peter Illitch Tchaikovsky; Premiere: 28 November 1915, Maryinsky Theater, Petrograd; 1937 version for Ballets Russes de Colonel W. de Basil: choreography by David Lichine
Fue Una Vez
Music: Carlos Gustavino; Premiere: 1942, Teatro Colón, Buenos Aires
The Good-Humored Ladies [Les Femmes de Bonne Humeur]
Choreographer: Léonide Massine; Music: Domenico Scarlatti, orchestrated by Vincenzo Tommasini; Premiere: 12 April 1917, Teatro Costanzi, Rome
Graduation Ball
Choreographer: David Lichine; Music: Johann Strauss, arranged by Anton Dorati; Premiere: 1940 (Australia)
Icare
Choreographer: Serge Lifar; Music: Szyfer, orchestrated by Arthur Honegger; Premiere: 1935 by the Paris Opera Ballet; restaged for Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, 1938
Les Imaginaires
Choreographer: David Lichine; Music: Georges Auric; Premiere: 1934
La Isla de los Ceibos
Jardin Public
Choreographer: Léonide Massine; Music: Vladimir Dukelsky [Vernon Duke]; Premiere: 1935
Jeux d’Enfants
Choreographer: Léonide Massine; Music: Georges Bizet; Premiere: 14 April 1932
Le Lion Amoureux
Choreographer: David Lichine; Music: Karol Rathaus; Premiere: 1937
Lutte Éternelle [The Eternal Struggle]
Choreographer: Igor Schwezoff; Music: Robert Schumann; Premiere: 29 July 1940, Theatre Royal, Sydney, Australia
El Malon
Mavra (opera)
Choreographer: Michel Fokine; Music: Igor Stravinsky; Premiere: 3 June 1922, Théâtre National de l’Opéra, Paris
Les Noces
Choreographer: Bronislava Nijinska; Music: Igor Stravinsky; Premiere: 13 June 1923, Théâtre de la Gaîté-Lyrique, Paris
Nocturne
Choreographer: David Lichine: Music: Jean Philippe Rameau, arranged by Roger Desormière; Premiere: 1933
Paganini
Choreographer: Michel Fokine; Music: Serge Rachmaninov; Premiere: 1938
Les Papillons
Choreographer: Michel Fokine; Music: Robert Schumann, orchestrated by Nicholas Tcherepnine; Premiere: 10 March 1912, Maryinsky Theater, Saint Petersburg; produced by the Ballets Russes on 16 April 1914 at the Théâtre de Monte-Carlo, Monte Carlo
Pavana [Pavane]
New version of Massine’s Las Meninias; music by Gabriel Fauré, choreographed by Serge Lifar for the Original Ballet Russe, Sydney, 1940
La Pavillon d’Armide
Choreographer: Michel Fokine; Music: Nicholas Tcherepnine; Premiere: 25 November 1907, Maryinsky Theater, Saint Petersburg; (Paris premiere: 18 May 1909, Théâtre du Châtelet)
Petruchka
Choreographer: Michel Fokine: Music: Igor Stravinsky; Premiere: 13 June 1911, Théâtre du Châtelet, Paris
Les Présages
Choreographer: Léonide Massine; Music: Petr Ill;ich Tchaikovsky; 1933
Protée
Choreographer: David Lichine; Music: Claude Debussy; Premiere: 1938
Pulcinella
Choreographer: Léonide Massine; Music: Igor Stravinsky, afte Giambattista Pergolesi; Premiere: 15 May 1920, Théâtre National de l’Opéra, Paris
Quest
Renard
Choreographer: Bronislava Nijinska; Music: Igor Stravinsky; Premiere: 18 May 1922, Théâtre National de l’Opéra, Paris
Romeo and Juliet
Choreographer: Bronislava Nijinska; Music: Constant Lambert; Premiere: 1926
Scuola di Ballo
Choreographer: Léonide Massine; Music: Luigi Boccherini, arranged by Jean Françaix; Premiere: 1933
Shérérazade
Choreographer: Michel Fokine; Music: Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov; Premiere: 4 June 1910, Théâtre National de l’Opéra, Paris
Le Soleil de Nuit [later Midnight Sun]
Choreographer: Léonide Massine; Music: Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov; Premiere: 20 December 1915, Grand Théâtre, Geneva
Le Spectre de la Rose
Choreographer: Michel Fokine: Music: Carl Maria von Weber, orchestrated by Hector Berlioz; Premiere: 19 April 1911, Théâtre de Monte-Carlo, Monte Carlo
Suite Choréographique
Les Sylphides
Choreographer: Michel Fokine: Music: Frédéric Chopin, orchestrated by Alexander Glazunov, Igor Stravinsky, Alexander Taneyev; Premiere: 2 June 1909, Théâtre du Châtelet
Swan Lake